<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kubernetes on Mikhail Shilkov</title>
    <link>https://mikhail.io/tags/kubernetes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Kubernetes on Mikhail Shilkov</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Mikhail Shilkov - All rights reserved</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://mikhail.io/tags/kubernetes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>AI-Assisted Infrastructure as Code with Pulumi&#39;s Model Context Protocol Server</title>
      <link>https://mikhail.io/2025/04/mcp-server-ai-assistants/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mikhail.io/2025/04/mcp-server-ai-assistants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Infrastructure as Code (IaC) has revolutionized how we manage cloud resources, but navigating complex cloud provider APIs, writing boilerplate code, and iterating through deployment cycles can still be time-consuming. Pulumi offers a fantastic developer experience using familiar programming languages. But what if we could make it even &lt;em&gt;faster&lt;/em&gt; and more intuitive by integrating powerful AI assistants directly into the development loop?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infrastructure as Code with Java and Pulumi</title>
      <link>https://mikhail.io/2022/05/infrastructure-as-code-with-java-and-pulumi/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mikhail.io/2022/05/infrastructure-as-code-with-java-and-pulumi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Infrastructure has become a core part of application development as modern cloud capabilities such as microservices, containers, serverless, and data stores define your application&amp;rsquo;s architecture. The term &amp;ldquo;infrastructure&amp;rdquo; covers all of the cloud resources your application needs to run. Modern architectures require thinking deeply about infrastructure while building your application, instead of treating it as an afterthought. Pulumi&amp;rsquo;s approach helps developers, infrastructure engineers, and platform teams work together to leverage everything the modern cloud has to offer.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How To Deploy Temporal to Azure Kubernetes Service (AKS)</title>
      <link>https://mikhail.io/2021/11/how-to-deploy-temporal-to-azure-kubernetes-aks/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mikhail.io/2021/11/how-to-deploy-temporal-to-azure-kubernetes-aks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my article &lt;a href=&#34;https://mikhail.io/2020/10/practical-approach-to-temporal-architecture/&#34;&gt;A Practical Approach to Temporal Architecture&lt;/a&gt;, I outlined the various &lt;a href=&#34;https://temporal.io/&#34;&gt;Temporal&lt;/a&gt; components and how they interact. Today&amp;rsquo;s blog builds on this knowledge and demonstrates an example of deploying Temporal to Kubernetes and, more specifically, to Azure Kubernetes Service (AKS).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How To Deploy Temporal to Azure Kubernetes Service (AKS)</title>
      <link>https://mikhail.io/2020/11/how-to-deploy-temporal-to-azure-kubernetes-aks/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mikhail.io/2020/11/how-to-deploy-temporal-to-azure-kubernetes-aks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my article &lt;a href=&#34;https://mikhail.io/2020/10/practical-approach-to-temporal-architecture/&#34;&gt;A Practical Approach to Temporal Architecture&lt;/a&gt;, I outlined the various &lt;a href=&#34;https://temporal.io/&#34;&gt;Temporal&lt;/a&gt; components and how they interact. Today’s blog builds on this knowledge and demonstrates an example of deploying Temporal to Kubernetes and, more specifically, to Azure Kubernetes Service (AKS).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How To Deploy a Function App with KEDA (Kubernetes-based Event-Driven Autoscaling)</title>
      <link>https://mikhail.io/2019/10/how-to-deploy-a-function-app-with-keda/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mikhail.io/2019/10/how-to-deploy-a-function-app-with-keda/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Azure Functions&lt;/strong&gt; is a managed service for serverless applications in the Azure cloud. More broadly, Azure Functions is a runtime with multiple hosting possibilities. &lt;strong&gt;KEDA&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://cloudblogs.microsoft.com/opensource/2019/05/06/announcing-keda-kubernetes-event-driven-autoscaling-containers/&#34;&gt;Kubernetes-based Event-Driven Autoscaling&lt;/a&gt;) is an emerging option to host this runtime in &lt;strong&gt;Kubernetes&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
