<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Java on Mikhail Shilkov</title>
    <link>https://mikhail.io/tags/java/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Java on Mikhail Shilkov</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Mikhail Shilkov - All rights reserved</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://mikhail.io/tags/java/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Infrastructure as Code with Java and Pulumi</title>
      <link>https://mikhail.io/2022/05/infrastructure-as-code-with-java-and-pulumi/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mikhail.io/2022/05/infrastructure-as-code-with-java-and-pulumi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Infrastructure has become a core part of application development as modern cloud capabilities such as microservices, containers, serverless, and data stores define your application&amp;rsquo;s architecture. The term &amp;ldquo;infrastructure&amp;rdquo; covers all of the cloud resources your application needs to run. Modern architectures require thinking deeply about infrastructure while building your application, instead of treating it as an afterthought. Pulumi&amp;rsquo;s approach helps developers, infrastructure engineers, and platform teams work together to leverage everything the modern cloud has to offer.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AWS Lambda: Cold Start Duration per Language</title>
      <link>https://mikhail.io/serverless/coldstarts/aws/languages/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mikhail.io/serverless/coldstarts/aws/languages/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The following chart shows the typical range of cold starts in AWS Lambda, broken down per language. The darker ranges are the most common 67% of durations, and lighter ranges include 95%.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Azure Functions: Cold Start Duration per Language</title>
      <link>https://mikhail.io/serverless/coldstarts/azure/languages/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mikhail.io/serverless/coldstarts/azure/languages/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The following chart shows the typical range of cold starts in Azure Functions, broken down per language. The darker ranges are the most common 67% of durations, and lighter ranges include 95%.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
