<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Containers on Mikhail Shilkov</title>
    <link>https://mikhail.io/tags/containers/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Containers on Mikhail Shilkov</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Mikhail Shilkov - All rights reserved</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://mikhail.io/tags/containers/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Deploying new Azure Container Apps with familiar languages</title>
      <link>https://mikhail.io/2021/11/azure-container-apps/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mikhail.io/2021/11/azure-container-apps/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, &lt;a href=&#34;https://aka.ms/containerapps/ignite-blog&#34;&gt;Microsoft announced&lt;/a&gt; a new general-purpose serverless container platform: &lt;a href=&#34;https://aka.ms/containerapps/&#34;&gt;Azure Container Apps&lt;/a&gt;. Container Apps is a fully managed platform for microservice applications that runs on top of Kubernetes and open-source technologies like KEDA, Envoy, and Dapr.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Container Apps are designed to abstract infrastructure management with flexible serverless containers. Developers can run containers at scale without the burden of standing up and managing a Kubernetes cluster manually.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We are happy to announce same-day support for Azure Container Apps in the Pulumi Azure Native Provider, which covers 100% of the Azure Resource Manager APIs and gives you highest fidelity integration with Azure&amp;rsquo;s resources.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Running Container Images in AWS Lambda</title>
      <link>https://mikhail.io/2020/12/aws-lambda-container-support/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mikhail.io/2020/12/aws-lambda-container-support/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When AWS Lambda launched in 2014, it pioneered the concept of Function-as-a-Service. Developers could write a function in one of the supported programming languages, upload it to AWS, and Lambda executes the function on every invocation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hosting Azure Functions in Google Cloud Run</title>
      <link>https://mikhail.io/2020/02/azure-functions-in-google-cloud-run/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mikhail.io/2020/02/azure-functions-in-google-cloud-run/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Suppose you are a .NET developer, you love the Function-as-a-Service (FaaS) model, but you want to run your serverless functions in Google Cloud. You want to keep using C# or F#, and still leverage all serverless benefits—ease of use, scalability, elasticity, pay-per-value cost model—running in GCP.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Serverless Containers with Google Cloud Run</title>
      <link>https://mikhail.io/2020/02/serverless-containers-with-google-cloud-run/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mikhail.io/2020/02/serverless-containers-with-google-cloud-run/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Google &lt;a href=&#34;https://cloud.google.com/run/&#34;&gt;Cloud Run&lt;/a&gt; is the latest addition to the serverless compute family. While it may look similar to existing services of public cloud, the feature set makes Cloud Run unique:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
