<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Infrastructure as Code on Mikhail Shilkov</title>
    <link>https://mikhail.io/tags/infrastructure-as-code/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Infrastructure as Code on Mikhail Shilkov</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Mikhail Shilkov - All rights reserved</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://mikhail.io/tags/infrastructure-as-code/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Choosing the Best Deployment Tool for Your Serverless Applications</title>
      <link>https://mikhail.io/2019/11/choosing-the-best-deployment-tool-for-serverless-applications/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mikhail.io/2019/11/choosing-the-best-deployment-tool-for-serverless-applications/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Function-as-a-Service solutions, such as AWS Lambda and Azure Functions, are a great way to build modern, scalable, and affordable cloud-native applications. By delegating routine work to cloud providers, serverless applications focus on custom logic to provide the ultimate business value. But, in fact, serverless is more than cloud functions. It&amp;rsquo;s storage, HTTP gateways, databases, queues, monitoring, and security&amp;mdash;and your serverless applications are likely to use multiple managed services and consist of many moving parts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Globally-distributed Serverless Application in 100 Lines of Code. Infrastructure Included!</title>
      <link>https://mikhail.io/2019/07/globally-distributed-serverless-application-in-100-lines-of-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mikhail.io/2019/07/globally-distributed-serverless-application-in-100-lines-of-code/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Pulumi is excellent at connecting multiple cloud components into a cohesive application. In my &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.pulumi.com/serverless-as-simple-callbacks-with-pulumi-and-azure-functions&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I introduced the way to mix JavaScript or TypeScript serverless functions directly into the cloud infrastructure programs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hosting a Static Website on Azure with Pulumi</title>
      <link>https://mikhail.io/2019/06/hosting-a-static-website-on-azure-with-pulumi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mikhail.io/2019/06/hosting-a-static-website-on-azure-with-pulumi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Static websites are back in the mainstream these days. Website generators like Jekyll, Hugo, or Gatsby, make it fairly easy to combine templates and markdown pages to produce static HTML files. Static assets are the simplest thing to serve and cache, so the whole setup ends up being fast and cost-efficient.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Serverless as Simple Callbacks with Pulumi and Azure Functions</title>
      <link>https://mikhail.io/2019/05/serverless-as-simple-callbacks-with-pulumi-and-azure-functions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mikhail.io/2019/05/serverless-as-simple-callbacks-with-pulumi-and-azure-functions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Serverless compute services, like Azure Functions, offer an amazing power to application developers to leverage: highly available, automatically scaled, low-ceremony, pay-per-value functions created in several lines of code.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Level up your Azure Platform as a Service applications with Pulumi</title>
      <link>https://mikhail.io/2019/05/level-up-your-azure-platform-as-a-service-applications-with-pulumi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mikhail.io/2019/05/level-up-your-azure-platform-as-a-service-applications-with-pulumi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Pulumi enables developers to define cloud infrastructure using general purpose programming languages. Pulumi works with multiple cloud providers and has first-class support for all services in Microsoft Azure.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
